Finding Aid for Lloyd E. Brownell papers, 1951-1960
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lloyd E. Brownell papers 1951-1960 1951-1954
Brownell, Lloyd E., 1915-1976.
1 linear foot
861083 Aa 2
Professor of chemical and nuclear engineering and director of the Fission Product Laboratory at The University of Michigan. Professional correspondence and reports largely concerning his interest in the use of radiation for preserving food.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the University of Michigan Dept. of Microbiology and the University Radiation Control Service (Donor nos. 4846 and 5666 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Lloyd E. Brownell was born on November 8, 1915 in Potsdam, New York. He attended Clarkson College, receiving a B.A. in chemical engineering in 1937 and a M.A. in mechanical engineering in 1939. After college he moved to Saginaw, Michigan to take a position at Baker Perkins, Inc., manufacturer of chemical and food machinery. Assigned to the development of food processing equipment, Brownell was sent by the company to the University of Michigan to perform research on foods at the College of Engineering. He decided to continue his education at the University, and completed his master's degree and doctorate in chemical engineering by 1947, afterwards joining the faculty as an associate professor of chemical engineering. He was promoted to full professor in 1954.
Maintaining his interest in food processing, Brownell specialized in research and teaching in this area, and participated in projects involving the industrial applications of radiation in food preservation and the development of a new technique for extracting sugar from sugar beets. He became head of the University's Fission Projects Laboratory in 1951, gained publicity as an expert in the atomic irradiation of foods for preservation, and served as consultant to the Atomic Energy Commission and to a number of industrial firms. In 1955 Brownell took part in the first United Nations Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy. Several years later he developed a synthetic rice substitute, Batina, to be used in supplementing the diets of third world populations. Brownell retired from the University of Michigan in the 1970s, and died in Richland, Washington in 1976.
The Lloyd Brownell papers consist largely of materials documenting Brownell's food irradiation experiments at the University of Michigan from 1951 to 1954. Other topics include experiments on the effects of radiation on petrochemical processes and pharmaceuticals and Brownell's work in sugar beet processing techniques. Beyond his work as a scientist, the collection also depicts the social climate of mid-1950s America, characterized by popular and industrial faith in progress and the powers of science. The collection has been divided into six series: Biographical/Bibliographical, Correspondence, Conferences, Projects, Articles and Programs, and Clippings.
Subjects:
Brownell, Lloyd E. (Lloyd Earl), 1915-; Food.; Irradiated foods.; Radiation.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Fission Products Laboratory.
- Biographical/Bibliographical
  - Obituary and bibliography (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1951-1954
  The series of Correspondence, the largest series in the collection, dates from 1951 to 1954, and consists of letters exchanged with various companies, agencies, professional organizations, and individuals. Topics covered include Brownell's work, his participation in conferences, and his authorship of papers and journal articles. These letters document the widespread interest in the prospects of food irradiation in this era of scientific optimism. Most are from 1953, but the files appear to be incomplete, for the middle of the alphabet is under-represented.
  - American (Box 1)
  - An-Az (Box 1)
  - B (Box 1)
  - C (Box 1)
  - D-E (Box 1)
  - F-G (Box 1)
  - H-O (Box 1)
  - P (Box 1)
  - Q-R (Box 1)
  - S (Box 1)
  - T (Box 1)
  - U (Box 1)
  - W (Box 1)
- Conferences
  Conferences is a smaller series of four folders with reports and minutes of various conferences and meetings relating to peacetime uses of nuclear energy, held at different locations from 1951 to 1954 that Brownell participated in. Two of the folders document Brownell's association with the American Institute of Chemical Engineers, and his participation in many of their conferences.
  - American Institute of Chemical Engineers, 1953-1954, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan, 1951-1954 (Box 1)
  - Various, 1951-1954 (Box 1)
- Projects
  Projects is a nine-folder series of miscellaneous project documents consisting of fragmented progress reports, grant and project proposals, budget information, proposed experimental procedures, and a full series of published reports on experiments carried out from 1954 to 1960 for the Quartermaster Food and Container Institute. Brownell was only peripherally associated with the latter series of experiments.
  - Atomic Energy Commission work reports, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Budgets, 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - Chick feeding experiments, undated (Box 1)
  - Progress Reports, 1951-1953 (Box 1)
  - Project proposals and correspondence, 1953-54 (Box 1)
  - Quartermaster Food and Container Institute reports, 1954-1960, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Articles and Programs
  - Miscellaneous, 1951-1954 (Box 1)
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous, 1953 (Box 1)